<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Created from PDF via Acrobat SaveAsXML -->
<!-- Mapping Table version: 28-February-2003 -->
<TaggedPDF-doc>
<?xpacket begin='﻿' id='W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d'?>
<?xpacket begin="﻿" id="W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d"?>
<x:xmpmeta xmlns:x="adobe:ns:meta/" x:xmptk="Adobe XMP Core 9.1-c001 79.2a0d8d9, 2023/03/14-11:19:46        ">
   <rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
      <rdf:Description rdf:about=""
            xmlns:xmp="http://ns.adobe.com/xap/1.0/"
            xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
            xmlns:xmpMM="http://ns.adobe.com/xap/1.0/mm/"
            xmlns:pdf="http://ns.adobe.com/pdf/1.3/">
         <xmp:ModifyDate>2024-01-11T15:21:59+05:30</xmp:ModifyDate>
         <xmp:CreateDate>2024-01-11T15:21:59+05:30</xmp:CreateDate>
         <xmp:MetadataDate>2024-01-11T15:21:59+05:30</xmp:MetadataDate>
         <xmp:CreatorTool>PScript5.dll Version 5.2.2</xmp:CreatorTool>
         <dc:format>xml</dc:format>
         <xmpMM:DocumentID>uuid:cd1d77c9-a1bb-4d8b-b153-804fedff9ae4</xmpMM:DocumentID>
         <xmpMM:InstanceID>uuid:342faedd-f8bd-44cd-991a-2507aa66f0f0</xmpMM:InstanceID>
         <pdf:Producer>Acrobat Distiller 23.0 (Windows)</pdf:Producer>
      </rdf:Description>
   </rdf:RDF>
</x:xmpmeta>
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                           
<?xpacket end="w"?>
<?xpacket end='r'?>
<bookmark-tree>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 1">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_895"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 2">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_896"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 3">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_897"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 4">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_898"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 5">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_899"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 6">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_900"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 7">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_901"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 8">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_902"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 9">
<destination structID="None"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 10">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_903"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 11">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_904"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 12">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_905"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 13">
<destination structID="None"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 14">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_906"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 15">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_907"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 16">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_908"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 17">
<destination structID="None"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 18">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_909"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 19">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_910"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 20">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_911"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated 21">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_286"/>
</bookmark>
</bookmark-tree>
<Figure id="LinkTarget_895">

<ImageData src="images/2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated - 2 chapters_img_0.jpg"/>
</Figure>
<Figure id="LinkTarget_896">

<ImageData src="images/2021 Virginia Existing Building Code 1st ptg updated - 2 chapters_img_1.jpg"/>
2021 Virginia Existing Building Code </Figure>

<P id="LinkTarget_897">2021 Virginia Existing Building Code </P>

<P>First Printing: September 2023 </P>

<P>ISBN: 978-1-960701-54-1 (soft-cover edition) ISBN: 978-1-960701-55-8 (PDF download) </P>

<P>COPYRIGHT © 2023 by INTERNATIONAL CODE COUNCIL, INC. </P>

<P>ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. This 2021 Virginia Existing Building Code contains substantial copyrighted material from the 2021 International Existing Building Code , second printing, which is a copyrighted work owned by the International Code Council, Inc. (“ICC”). Without separate written permission from the copyright owner, no part of this publication may be reproduced, distributed or transmitted in any form or by any means, including, without limitation, electronic, optical or mechanical means (by way of example, and not limitation, photocopying or recording by or in an information storage and/or retrieval system). For information on use rights and permissions, please contact: ICC Publications, 4051 Flossmoor Road, Country Club Hills, Illinois 60478; 1-888-ICC-SAFE (422-7233); https://www.iccsafe.org/about/periodicals-and-newsroom/icc-logo-license/. </P>

<P>Trademarks: “International Code Council,” the “International Code Council” logo, “ICC,” the “ICC” logo, “International Existing Building Code,” “IEBC” and other names and trademarks appearing in this publication are registered trademarks of the International Code Council, Inc., and/or its licensors (as applicable), and may not be used without permission. </P>

<P>PRINTED IN THE USA </P>

<P>T029380 </P>

<Part>
<H2 id="LinkTarget_898">PREFACE </H2>

<Sect>
<H3>Introduction </H3>

<P>The Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (USBC) is a state regulation promulgated by the Virginia Board of Housing and Community Development, a Governor-appointed board, for the purpose of establishing minimum regulations to govern the construction and maintenance of buildings and structures. </P>

<P>The provisions of the USBC are based on nationally recognized model building and fire codes published by the International Code Council, Inc. The model codes are made part of the USBC through a regulatory process known as incorporation by reference. The USBC also contains administrative provisions governing the use of the model codes and establishing requirements for the enforcement of thecode by the local building departments and other code enforcement agencies. </P>

<P>In keeping with the designations of the USBC used previously, since the 2021 editions of the Inter</P>

<P>national Codes are incorporated by reference into this version of the USBC, it is known as the 2021 </P>

<Sect>
<P>edition of the USBC. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Arrangement </H3>

<P>The USBC is part of the Virginia Administrative Code (VAC), the official compilation of state regulationspublished under the authority and guidance of the Virginia Code Commission. Due to the difference inthe section numbering system between the VAC and the model codes incorporated by reference intothe USBC, the USBC utilizes a dual section numbering system. In the USBC, the VAC section numbers are listed first, followed by a section number matching the model code system. In this printing of the USBC, the VAC section numbers are omitted and only the model code numbering system is utilized. The version of the USBC containing both the VAC section numbers and the model code numbering canbe accessed through Virginia’s Legislative Information System (LIS) here: https://law.lis.virginia.gov/ admincode/title13/agency5/. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Overview </H3>

<P>The USBC is divided into three stand-alone parts. Part I contains regulations specific to the construction of new buildings and structures and is known as the Virginia Construction Code. Part II contains regulations specific to the rehabilitation of existing buildings, including repair, alterations, additionsand change of occupancy in existing buildings and structures, and is known as the Virginia Existing Building Code. Part III of the USBC contains the regulations for the maintenance of existing structures which is enforced at the option of the local governments. It is known as the Virginia Maintenance Code. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Codes Purchased from ICC </H3>

<P>The 2021 edition of the USBC is being made available in pamphlet form as in past editions of the USBC. Inaddition to the pamphlet form of the USBC published by DHCD, the International Code Council (ICC) publishes versions of the Virginia Construction Code, Virginia Existing Building Code, Virginia Maintenance Code and a series of Virginia specific trade codes. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3 id="LinkTarget_899">Marginal Markings </H3>

<P>In the ICC published versions, marginal markings are provided to distinguish between text which is part of the International Codes and text which is part of the state regulations. Double vertical linesin the margins within the body of the codes indicate state amendments to the International Codes.As in the standard printings of the International Codes, a single vertical line in the margins within the body of the code indicates a technical change from the previous edition of the International Codes. </P>

<P>Deletions from the previous editions of the International Codes are indicated in the form of an arrow () in the margin where an entire section, paragraph, exception or table has been deleted or an item in a list of items or a table has been deleted. Deletions to the Virginia Code are indicated with an open caret (&gt;) in the margin. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Technical Assistance </H3>

<P>The local building departments and enforcing agencies may be contacted for further information concerning the USBC. Contact information for the State Building Codes Office is below. </P>

<P>DHCD, Division of Building and Fire RegulationState Building Codes Office600 East Main Street, Suite 300 Richmond, Virginia 23219Phone: (804) 371-7150 – Email: sbco@dhcd.virginia.govWebsite: www.dhcd.virginia.gov/codes </P>

<Sect/>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3 id="LinkTarget_900">PREVIOUS ADOPTIONS and AMENDMENTS of the USBC and SFPC </H3>

<P>The Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (USBC) was first adopted in 1973 by the State Board of Housing. Responsibility for the USBC passed to the State Board of Housing and Community Development on July 1, 1978. The Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code was first adopted by the Board of Housing and Community Development on March 1, 1988. The initial adoption and subsequent amendments by these Boards are indicated below: </P>

<P>1973 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: September 1, 1973 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Administrative Amendments, 1973 Edition Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1970, with </P>

<P>1972 Accumulative Supplement BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1971 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1970, with </P>

<P>1972 Accumulative Supplement CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/1971 NFPA National Electrical Code/1971 </P>

<P>1974 Accumulative Supplement </P>

<P>Effective date: April 1, 1974 Title: 1974 Accumulative Supplement to Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1970, with </P>

<P>1972 Accumulative Supplement BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1971 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1970, with </P>

<P>1972 Accumulative Supplement NFPA National Electrical Code/1971 </P>

<P>1975 Accumulative Supplement </P>

<P>Effective date: February 7, 1976 Title: 1975 Accumulative Supplement to Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1975 BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1975 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1975 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/1975 NFPA National Electrical Code/1975 </P>

<P>1978 Accumulative Supplement </P>

<P>Effective date: August 1, 1978 Title: 1978 Accumulative Supplement to Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1978 BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1978 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1978 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/1975 NFPA National Electrical Code/1978 </P>

<P>1978 Accumulative Supplement (First Amendment) </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective date: January 1, 1981 NOTE: The 1978 Accumulative Supplement to the Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code was continued, but with a few changes to the previously referenced BOCA Basic Building Code/1978. </P>
</Sect>

<P>1981 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective date: July 16, 1982 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, 1981 Edition Major reference standards: </P>

<P>BOCA Basic Building Code/1981 BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1981 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1981 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/ </P>

<P>1979 with 1980 Amendments NFPA National Electrical Code/1981 </P>
</Sect>

<P>1981 Edition (First Amendment) </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective date: June 20, 1984 Title: Sections 515.4 and 515.5 of Article 5 of the 1981 Edition, Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code </P>
</Sect>

<P>1984 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective date: April 1, 1986 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1984 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1984 BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1984 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1984 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/ </P>

<P>1983 with 1984 Amendments NFPA National Electrical Code/1984 </P>
</Sect>

<P>1987 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective date: March 1, 1988 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1987 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA Basic Building Code/1987 BOCA Basic Mechanical Code/1987 BOCA Basic Plumbing Code/1987 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/ </P>

<P>1986 with 1987 Amendments </P>

<P>NFPA National Electrical Code/1987 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 1987 Edition Major reference standard: </P>

<P>BOCA National Fire Prevention Code/1987 </P>
</Sect>

<P id="LinkTarget_901">1987 Edition (First Amendment) </P>

<P>Effective date: March 1, 1989 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1987 Edition Major reference standards: Same as 1987 Edition </P>

<P>1987 Edition (Second Amendment) </P>

<P>Effective date: March 1, 1990 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1987 Edition Major reference standards: Same as 1987 Edition </P>

<P>1987 Edition (Third Amendment) </P>

<P>Effective date: October 1, 1990 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1987 Edition Major reference standards: Same as 1987 Edition </P>

<P>1990 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: March 1, 1991 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1990 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA National Building Code/1990 BOCA National Mechanical Code/1990 BOCA National Plumbing Code/1990 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling </P>

<P>Code/1989 with 1990 Amendments </P>

<P>NFPA National Electrical Code/1990 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 1990 Edition Major reference standard: </P>

<P>BOCA National Fire Prevention Code/1990 </P>

<P>1990 Edition (First Amendment) </P>

<P>Effective date: November 1, 1991 </P>

<P>Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1990 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: Same as 1990 Edition </P>

<P>1990 Edition (Third Amendment) </P>

<P>Effective date: March 1, 1993 </P>

<P>Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1990 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: Same as 1990 Edition. </P>

<P>1993 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: April 1, 1994 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Volume I—New Construction Code, 1993 Edition </P>

<P>Major reference standards: BOCA National Building Code/1993 BOCA National Fire Prevention Code/1993 BOCA National Mechanical Code/1993 BOCA National Plumbing Code/1993 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/ </P>

<Sect>
<P>1992 with 1993 Amendments </P>
</Sect>

<P>NFPA National Electrical Code/1993 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 1993 Edition Major reference standard: </P>

<P>BOCA National Fire Prevention Code/1993 </P>

<P>1996 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: April 15, 1997 with minor revision </P>

<P>August 20, 1997 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, 1996 Edition Major reference standards: </P>

<P>BOCA National Building Code/1996 CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code/1995 ICC International Mechanical Code/1996 ICC International Plumbing Code/1995 with </P>

<Sect>
<P>1996 Supplement </P>
</Sect>

<P>NFPA National Electrical Code/1996 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 1996 Edition Major reference standard: </P>

<P>BOCA National Fire Prevention Code/1996 </P>

<P>1996 Edition w/2000 Amendments </P>

<P>Effective date: September 15, 2000 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, 1996 Edition with 2000 Amendments Major reference standards: Same as 1996 edition except with ICC International Fuel Gas Code 1997 </P>

<P>2000 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: October 1, 2003 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2000 Edition) </P>

<P>Major referenced standards: ICC International Code Council (ICC) ICC International Building Code 2000 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2000 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2000 ICC International Mechanical Code 2000 ICC International Plumbing Code 2000 ICC International Residential Code 2000 NFPA National Electrical Code 1999 </P>

<P>NOTE: An amendment addressing the fire separation distance between dwellings under the IRC became effective on September 9, 2004. Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2000 Edition Major reference standard: </P>

<P>ICC International Fire Code 2000 </P>

<Sect/>

<P id="LinkTarget_902">2003 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: November 16, 2005 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2003 Edition) Major referenced standards: International Code Council (ICC) ICC International Building Code 2003 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2003 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2003 ICC International Mechanical Code 2003 ICC International Plumbing Code 2003 ICC International Residential Code 2003 NFPA National Electrical Code 2005 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2003 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2003 </P>

<P>2006 Edition </P>

<P>Effective date: May 1, 2008 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2006 Edition) Major referenced standards: ICC International Building Code 2006 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2006 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2006 ICC International Mechanical Code 2006 ICC International Plumbing Code 2006 ICC International Residential Code 2006 NFPA National Electrical Code 2005 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2006 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2006 </P>

<P>2009 Edition </P>

<P>Effective Date: March 1, 2011 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2009 Edition) Major referenced standards: ICC International Building Code 2009 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2009 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2009 ICC International Mechanical Code 2009 ICC International Plumbing Code 2009 ICC International Residential Code 2009 NFPA National Electrical Code 2008 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2009 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2009 </P>

<P>2012 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective Date: July 14, 2014 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2012 Edition) Major referenced standards: ICC International Building Code 2012 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2012 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2012 ICC International Mechanical Code 2012 ICC International Plumbing Code 2012 ICC International Residential Code 2012 NFPA National Electrical Code 2011 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2012 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2012 </P>
</Sect>

<P>2015 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective Date: September 4, 2018 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2015 Edition) Major referenced standards: ICC International Building Code 2015 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2015 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2015 ICC International Mechanical Code 2015 ICC International Plumbing Code 2015 ICC International Residential Code 2015 NFPA National Electrical Code 2014 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2015 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2015 </P>
</Sect>

<P>2018 Edition </P>

<Sect>
<P>Effective Date: July 1, 2021 Title: Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code (2018 Edition) Major referenced standards: ICC International Building Code 2018 ICC International Energy Conservation Code 2018 ICC International Fuel Gas Code 2018 ICC International Mechanical Code 2018 ICC International Plumbing Code 2018 ICC International Residential Code 2018 NFPA National Electrical Code 2017 Title: Virginia Statewide Fire Prevention Code, 2018 Edition Major reference standard: ICC International Fire Code 2018 </P>
</Sect>

<Sect/>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2 id="LinkTarget_903">TABLE OF CONTENTS </H2>

<Sect>
<P>CHAPTER 1 ADMINISTRATION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1-1 </P>

<P>Section </P>

<P>101 General. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1-1 102 Purpose and Scope. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1-2 103 Application of Code. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1-3 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 2 DEFINITIONS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2-1 </P>

<P>Section 201 General. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2-1 202 General Definitions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 3 GENERAL PROVISIONS </P>

<P>AND SPECIAL DETAILED </P>

<P>REQUIREMENTS. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-1 Section 301 General. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-1 302 Building Materials and Systems . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-1 303 Fire Escapes. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-1 304 Glass Replacement and Replacement Windows. . . 3-2 305 Seismic Force-Resisting Systems . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-2 306 Higher Education Laboratories . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3-3 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 4 ACCESSIBILITY. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-1 </P>

<P>Section 401 General. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-1 402 Change of Occupancy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-1 403 Additions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-1 404 Alterations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-1 405 Historic Buildings . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4-3 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 5 REPAIRS. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-1 </P>

<P>Section 501 General. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-1 502 Structural . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-1 503 Flood Hazard Areas . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-2 504 Electrical . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-2 505 Mechanical. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-2 506 Plumbing . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-3 507 Energy Conservation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5-3 </P>
</Sect>

<P>CHAPTER 6 ALTERATIONS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6-1 </P>

<P>Section 601 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6-1 602 Alteration—Level1  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6-2 603 Alteration—Level2. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6-4 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 7 CHANGE OF OCCUPANCY. . . . . . . 7-1 </P>

<P>Section 701 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-1 702 Special Use and Occupancy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-1 703 Building Elements and Materials . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-1 704 Fire Protection. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-1 705 Means of Egress . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-2 706 Heights and Areas . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-4 707 Exterior Wall Fire-Resistance Ratings . . . . . . . . . 7-4 708 Electrical and Lighting . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-5 709 Mechanical and Ventilation. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-5 710 Plumbing . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-5 711 Structural . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-5 712 Accessibility . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7-6 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 8 ADDITIONS. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-1 </P>

<P>Section 801 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-1 802 Heights and Areas . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-1 803 Structural . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-1 804 Flood Hazard Areas. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-2 805 Energy Conservation. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8-2 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 9 HISTORIC BUILDINGS . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 </P>

<P>Section 901 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 902 Flood Hazard Areas. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 903 Repairs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 904 (Reserved) .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 905 Alterations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-1 906 Change of Occupancy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-2 907 Structural . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9-2 </P>

<Sect/>

<P id="LinkTarget_904">TABLE OF CONTENTS </P>

<P>CHAPTER 10 MOVED BUILDINGS AND STRUCTURES . . . . . . . . . . . .10-1 </P>

<P>Section 1001 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .10-1 1002 Requirements. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .10-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 11 RETROFIT REQUIREMENTS . . . 11-1 </P>

<P>Section 1101 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .11-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 12 CONSTRUCTION SAFEGUARDS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-1 </P>

<P>Section 1201 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-1 1202 Protection of Adjoining Properties . . . . . . . . . . . 12-2 1203 Temporary Use of Streets, Alleys and Public Property. . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-2 1204 Fire Extinguishers. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 1205 Means of Egress . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 1206 Standpipe Systems. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 1207 Automatic Sprinkler System . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 1208 Accessibility . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 1209 Water Supply for Fire Protection . . . . . . . . . . . . 12-3 1210 Demolition. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12-3 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 13 REFERENCED STANDARDS . . . . 13-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER 14 COMPLIANCE ALTERNATIVE– CHANGE OF OCCUPANCY . . . . . 14-1 </P>

<P>Section 1401 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .14-1 1402 Evaluation Process . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .14-1 1403 Evaluation Data. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .14-1 1404 Evaluation Scores . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .14-8 </P>

<P>APPENDIX A GUIDELINES FOR THE SEISMIC RETROFIT OF EXISTING BUILDINGS . . . . . . . . .APPENDIX A-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER A1 SEISMIC STRENGTHENING PROVISIONS FOR UNREINFORCED MASONRY BEARING WALL BUILDINGS . . . . . . . . .APPENDIX A-1 </P>

<P>Section A101 Purpose . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-1 A102 Scope. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-1 A103 Definitions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-1 A104 Symbols and Notations . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-2 A105 General Requirements. . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-3 A106 Materials Requirements . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-4 A107 Quality Control . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-5 A108 Design Strengths. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-6 A109 Analysis and Design Procedure . . . APPENDIX A-6 A110 General Procedure. . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-7 A111 Special Procedure .. . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-8 A112 Analysis and Design . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-11 A113 Detailed Building System </P>

<P>Design Requirements. . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-13 A114 Walls of Unburned Clay, </P>

<Sect>
<P>Adobe or Stone Masonry . . . . . APPENDIX A-14 </P>
</Sect>

<P>CHAPTER A2 EARTHQUAKE HAZARD </P>

<Sect>
<P>REDUCTION IN EXISTING </P>

<P>REINFORCED CONCRETE AND </P>

<P>REINFORCED MASONRY WALL </P>

<P>BUILDINGS WITH FLEXIBLE </P>
</Sect>

<P>DIAPHRAGMS. . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 Section A201 Purpose . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 A202 Scope. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 A203 Definitions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 A204 Symbols and Notations . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 A205 General Requirements. . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-15 A206 Analysis and Design . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-16 A207 Materials of Construction . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-17 </P>

<P>CHAPTER A3 PRESCRIPTIVE PROVISIONS </P>

<Sect>
<P>FOR SEISMIC STRENGTHENING </P>

<P>OF CRIPPLE WALLS AND </P>

<P>SILL PLATE ANCHORAGE </P>

<P>OF LIGHT, WOOD-FRAME </P>

<P>RESIDENTIAL </P>
</Sect>

<P>BUILDINGS . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-19 Section A301 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-19 A302 Definitions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-19 A303 Structural Weaknesses . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-20 A304 Strengthening Requirements. . . . . APPENDIX A-20 </P>

<Sect>
<P id="LinkTarget_905">TABLE OF CONTENTS </P>

<P>CHAPTER A4 EARTHQUAKE RISK REDUCTION IN WOOD-FRAME RESIDENTIAL BUILDINGS WITH SOFT, WEAK OR OPEN FRONT WALLS . . . . .APPENDIX A-37 </P>

<P>Section A401 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-37 A402 Definitions. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-37 A403 Analysis and Design . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-37 </P>

<P>A404 Prescriptive Measures for Weak Story . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-39 A405 Materials of Construction . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-40 A406 Construction Documents . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-40 A407 Quality Control . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-41 </P>

<P>CHAPTER A5 REFERENCED STANDARDS . . . . . . .APPENDIX A-43 </P>

<P>Section A501 Referenced Standards . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX A-43 </P>

<P>APPENDIX B SUPPLEMENTARY ACCESSIBILITY REQUIREMENTS FOR EXISTING BUILDINGS AND FACILITIES . . . . APPENDIX B-1 </P>

<P>Section B101 Qualified Historic Buildings and Facilities . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX B-1 B102 Fixed Transportation Facilities and Stations. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX B-1 B103 Dwelling Units and Sleeping Units . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX B-2 B104 Referenced Standards . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX B-2 </P>

<P>APPENDIX C GUIDELINES FOR THE WIND RETROFIT OF EXISTING BUILDINGS . . . . . . . . .APPENDIX C-1 </P>

<P>CHAPTER C1 GABLE END RETROFIT FOR HIGH-WIND AREAS. . . . . . . . . . . . . .APPENDIX C-1 </P>

<P>Section C101 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-1 C102 Definitions. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-1 C103 Materials of Construction . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-2 C104 Retrofitting Gable End Walls to Enhance Wind Resistance . . . . . . APPENDIX C-4 </P>
</Sect>

<P>CHAPTER C2 ROOF DECK FASTENING FOR HIGH-WIND AREAS. . . . . . . . . . . . .APPENDIX C-21 </P>

<P>Section C201 General . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-21 C202 Roof Deck Attachment for Wood Roofs. . . . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-21 </P>

<P>CHAPTER C3 REFERENCED STANDARDS . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-23 </P>

<P>Section C301 Referenced Standards . . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX C-23 </P>

<P>APPENDIX D BOARD OF APPEALS (DELETED). . . . . . . . . . APPENDIX D-1 </P>

<P>RESOURCE A GUIDELINES ON FIRE RATINGS OF ARCHAIC MATERIALS AND ASSEMBLIES. . . . . . . RESOURCE A-1 </P>

<P>Section 1 Fire-Related Performance of Archaic Materials and Assemblies . . . . . . RESOURCE A-2 2 Building Evaluation . . . . . . . . . . . . . RESOURCE A-3 3 Final Evaluation and Design Solution . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .RESOURCE A-6 4 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .RESOURCE A-13 Appendix . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .RESOURCE A-15 Resource A Table of Contents. . . .RESOURCE A-15 Bibliography . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .RESOURCE A-134 </P>

<Sect/>

<P id="LinkTarget_906">CHAPTER 1 </P>

<Sect>
<H3>ADMINISTRATION </H3>

<Sect>
<P>SECTION 101 GENERAL </P>
</Sect>

<P>101.1 Short title. The Virginia Uniform Statewide Building Code, Part II, Existing Buildings, may be cited as the “Virginia Existing Building Code” or as the “VEBC.” </P>

<Sect>
<P>101.2 Incorporation by reference. Chapters 2–16 of the 2021 International Existing Building Code®, published by the International Code Council, Inc., are adopted and incorporated by reference to be an enforceable part of the VEBC. The term “IEBC®” means the 2021 International Existing Building Code, published by the International Code Council, Inc. Any codes and standards referenced in the IEBC are also considered to be part of the incorporation by reference, except that such codes and standards are used only to the prescribed extent of each such reference. </P>
</Sect>

<P>101.3 Numbering system. A dual numbering system is used in the VEBC to correlate the numbering system of the Virginia Administrative Code with the numbering system of the IEBC. IEBC numbering system designations are provided in the catchlines of the Virginia Administrative Code sections and cross references between sections or chapters of the VEBC use only the IEBC numbering system designations. The term “chapter” is used in the context of the numbering system of the IEBC and may mean a chapter in the VEBC, a chapter in the IEBC or a chapter in a referenced code or standard, depending on the context of the use of the term. The term “chapter” is not used to designate a chapter of the Virginia Administrative Code, unless clearly indicated. </P>

<P>101.4 Arrangement of code provisions. The VEBC is comprised of the combination of (i) the provisions of Chapter 1, Administration, which are established herein, (ii) Chapters 2– 16 of the IEBC, which are incorporated by reference in Section 101.2, and (iii) the changes to the text of the incorporated chapters of the IEBC that are specifically identified, including any new chapters added. The terminology “changes to the text of the incorporated chapters of the IEBC that are specifically identified, including any new chapters added” shall also be referred to as the “state amendments to the IEBC.” Such state amendments to the IEBC are set out using corresponding chapter and section numbers of the IEBC numbering system. In addition, since Chapter 1 of the IEBC is not incorporated as part of the VEBC, any reference to a provision of Chapter 1 of the IEBC in the provisions of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC is generally invalid. However, where the purpose of such a reference would clearly correspond to a provision of Chapter 1 established herein, then the reference may be construed to be a valid reference to such corresponding Chapter 1 provision. </P>

<Sect>
<P>101.5 Use of terminology and notes. The provisions of this code shall be used as follows: </P>
</Sect>

<P>1. The term “this code,” or “the code,” where used in the provisions of Chapter 1, in Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC, or in the state amendments to the IEBC, means the VEBC, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. </P>

<Sect>
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>The term “this code,” or “the code,” where used in a code or standard referenced in the VEBC, means that code or standard, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>The term “USBC,” where used in this code, means the Virginia Construction Code (VCC), unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>4. </Lbl>

<LBody>The use of notes in Chapter 1 is to provide information only and shall not be construed as changing the meaning of any code provision. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>5. </Lbl>

<LBody>Notes in the IEBC, in the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC and in the state amendments to the IEBC may modify the content of a related provision and shall be considered to be a valid part of the provision, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>6. </Lbl>

<LBody>References to International Codes and standards, where used in this code, include state amendments made to those International Codes and standards in the VCC. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Note: See Section 101.2 of the VCC for a list of major codes and standards referenced in the VCC. </P>
</Sect>

<P>101.6 Order of precedence. The provisions of this code shall be used as follows: </P>

<Sect>
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>The provisions of Chapter 1 of this code supersede any provisions of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC that address the same subject matter and impose differing requirements. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>The provisions of Chapter 1 of this code supersede any provisions of the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC that address the same subject matter and impose differing requirements. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>The state amendments to the IEBC supersede any provisions of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC that address the same subject matter and impose differing requirements. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>4. </Lbl>

<LBody>The state amendments to the IEBC supersede any provisions of the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC that address the same subject matter and impose differing requirements. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>5. </Lbl>

<LBody>The provisions of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC supersede any provisions of the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC that address the same subject matter and impose differing requirements. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<P>101.7 Administrative provisions. The provisions of Chapter 1 establish administrative requirements, which include but are not limited to provisions relating to the scope and enforcement of the code. Any provisions of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC or any provisions of the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC that address the same subject matter to a lesser or greater extent are deleted and replaced by the provisions of Chapter 1. Further, any administrative </P>

<Sect/>

<P id="LinkTarget_907">ADMINISTRATION </P>

<P>requirements contained in the state amendments to the IEBC shall be given the same precedence as the provisions of Chapter 1. Notwithstanding the above, where administrative requirements of Chapters 2–16 of the IEBC or of the codes and standards referenced in the IEBC are specifically identified as valid administrative requirements in Chapter 1 of this code or in the state amendments to the IEBC, then such requirements are not deleted and replaced. </P>

<P>Note: The purpose of this provision is to eliminate overlap, conflicts and duplication by providing a single standard for administrative, procedural and enforcement requirements of this code. </P>

<P>101.8 Definitions. The definitions of terms used in this code are contained in Chapter 2 along with specific provisions addressing the use of definitions. Terms may be defined in other chapters or provisions of the code and such definitions are also valid. </P>

<Sect>
<P>SECTION 102 PURPOSE AND SCOPE </P>
</Sect>

<P>102.1 Purpose. In accordance with § 36-99.01 of the Code of Virginia, the General Assembly of Virginia has declared that (i) there is an urgent need to improve the housing conditions of low and moderate income individuals and families, many of whom live in substandard housing, particularly in the older cities of the Commonwealth; (ii) there are large numbers of older residential buildings in the Commonwealth, both occupied and vacant, which are in urgent need of rehabilitation and must be rehabilitated if the state’s citizens are to be housed in decent, sound, and sanitary conditions; and (iii) the application of those building code requirements currently in force to housing rehabilitation has sometimes led to the imposition of costly and time-consuming requirements that result in a significant reduction in the amount of rehabilitation activity taking place. </P>

<P>The General Assembly further declares that (i) there is an urgent need to improve the existing condition of many of the Commonwealth’s stock of commercial properties, particularly in older cities; (ii) there are large numbers of older commercial buildings in the Commonwealth, both occupied and vacant, that are in urgent need of rehabilitation and that must be rehabilitated if the citizens of the Commonwealth are to be provided with decent, sound and sanitary work spaces; and (iii) the application of the existing building code to such rehabilitation has sometimes led to the imposition of costly and time-consuming requirements that result in a significant reduction in the amount of rehabilitation activity taking place. </P>

<P>102.2 Scope. The provisions of this code shall govern construction and rehabilitation activities in existing buildings and structures. </P>

<P>102.2.1 Change of occupancy to Group I-2 or I-3. A change of occupancy to Group I-2 or I-3 from another occupancy classification shall comply with the provisions of the VCC as required for new construction, not Chapter 7 of this code. All other provisions of the VEBC, including change of occupancy within an existing Group I-2 or I3 classification, are applicable to Group I-2 or I-3. </P>

<P>102.2.2 Reconstruction, alteration, or repair in GroupR-5 occupancies. Compliance with this section shall be an acceptable alternative to compliance with this code at the discretion of the owner or owner’s agent. The VCC may be used for the reconstruction, alteration, or repair of Group R-5 buildings or structures subject to the following criteria: </P>

<Sect>
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>Any reconstruction, alteration or repair shall not adversely affect the performance of the building or structure, or cause the building or structure to become unsafe or lower existing levels of health and safety. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Parts of the building or structure not being reconstructed, altered, or repaired shall not be required to comply with the requirements of the VCC applicable to newly constructed buildings or structures. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>The installation of material or equipment, or both, that is neither required nor prohibited shall only be required to comply with the provisions of the VCC relating to the safe installation of such material or equipment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>4. </Lbl>

<LBody>Material or equipment, or both, may be replaced in the same location with material or equipment of a similar kind or capacity. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>5. </Lbl>

<LBody>In accordance with § 36-99.2 of the Code of Virginia, installation or replacement of glass shall comply with Section R308 or Chapter 24 of the VCC. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Exceptions: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>This section shall not be construed to permit noncompliance with any applicable flood load or flood-resistant construction requirements of the VCC. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Reconstructed decks, balconies, porches, and similar structures located 30 inches (762 mm) or more above grade shall meet the current code provisions for structural loading capacity, connections, and structural attachment. This requirement excludes the configuration and height of handrails and guardrails. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>Repair or replacement of smoke alarms shall be with devices listed in accordance with UL217 and that are no more than 10 years from the date of manufacture. Battery-only powered devices shall be powered by a 10-year sealed battery. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<P>102.2.3 Additions. Where one or more newly constructed fire walls that comply with Section 706 of the VCC is provided between an addition and the existing building or structure or portions thereof, the addition shall be considered a separate building, and therefore, not an addition within the scope of this code. Such separate building, including the fire wall, shall be constructed in accordance with the VCC and shall not place the existing building or structure in nonconformance with the building code under which the existing building or structure or the affected portions thereof was built, or as previously approved. </P>

<Sect>
<P id="LinkTarget_908">SECTION 103 APPLICATION OF CODE </P>
</Sect>

<P>103.1 General. All administrative provisions of the VCC, including requirements for permits, inspections and approvals by the local building department, provisions for appeals from decisions of the local building department and the issuance of modifications, are applicable to the use of this code, except where this code sets out differing requirements. Where there is a conflict between a general requirement and a specific requirement in the VEBC, the specific requirement shall govern. </P>

<P>103.1.1Use of performance code. Compliance with the provisions of a nationally recognized performance code when approved as a modification shall be considered to constitute compliance with this code. All documents submitted as part of such consideration shall be retained in the permanent records of the local building department. </P>

<P>103.1.2Preliminary meeting. When requested by a prospective permit applicant or when determined necessary by the code official, the code official shall meet with the prospective permit applicant prior to the application for a permit to discuss plans for the proposed work or change of occupancy in order to establish the specific applicability of the provisions of this code. </P>

<P>103.2 Change of occupancy. A building or structure undergoing a change of occupancy shall comply with the provisions of this code for change of occupancy except as provided for in Section 102.2.1 for Group I-2 or I-3. Permitting, inspections and certificate of occupancy issuance shall be in accordance with the administrative provisions of the VCC. </P>

<Sect>
<P>When impractical to achieve compliance with this code for the new occupancy, the building official shall consider modifications upon application and as provided for in Section </P>

<P>106.3 of the VCC. </P>
</Sect>

<P>103.3 Retrofit requirements. The local building department shall enforce the provisions of Section 1101 that require certain existing buildings to be retrofitted with fire protection systems and other safety equipment. Retroactive fire protection system requirements contained in the International Fire Code shall not be applicable unless required for compliance with the provisions of Section 1101. </P>

<P>103.4 Nonrequired equipment. The following criteria for nonrequired equipment are in accordance with § 36-103 of the Code of Virginia. Building owners may elect to install partial or full fire alarms or other safety equipment that was not required by the edition of the VCC in effect at the time a building was constructed without meeting current requirements of the code, provided the installation does not create a hazardous condition. Permits for installation shall be obtained in accordance with the VCC. In addition, as a requirement of this code, when such nonrequired equipment is to be installed, the building official shall notify the appropriate fire official or fire chief. </P>

<Sect>
<P>103.4.1 Reduction in function or discontinuance of nonrequired fire protection systems. When a nonrequired fire protection system is to be reduced in function or discontinued, it shall be done in such a manner so as not </P>

<P>ADMINISTRATION </P>

<P>to create a false sense of protection. Generally, in such cases, any features visible from interior areas shall be removed, such as sprinkler heads, smoke detectors, or alarm panels or devices, but any wiring or piping hidden within the construction of the building may remain. Approval of the proposed method of reduction or discontinuance shall be obtained from the building official. </P>
</Sect>

<P>103.5 Requirements relating to maintenance. Any requirements of the IEBC requiring the maintenance of existing buildings or structures are invalid. </P>

<Sect>
<P>Note: Requirements for the maintenance of existing buildings and structures and for unsafe conditions are contained in the Virginia Property Maintenance Code (VPMC). </P>
</Sect>

<P>103.6 Use of Appendix A. Appendix A of the IEBC provides guidelines for the seismic retrofit of existing buildings. The use of this appendix is not mandatory but shall be permitted to be utilized at the option of an owner, the owner’s agent or the registered design professional (RDP) involved in a rehabilitation project. However, in no case shall the use of Appendix A be construed to authorize the lowering of existing levels of health or safety in buildings or structures being rehabilitated. </P>

<P>103.7 Use of Appendix B. Appendix B of the IEBC provides supplementary accessibility requirements for existing buildings and facilities. All applicable requirements of Appendix B shall be met in buildings and structures being rehabilitated. </P>

<P>103.8 Use of Resource A. Resource A of the IEBC provides guidelines for the evaluation of fire-resistance ratings of archaic materials and may be used in conjunction with rehabilitation projects. </P>

<P>103.9 Construction documents. Construction documents shall be submitted with the application for a permit. The work proposed to be performed on an existing building or structure shall be classified on the construction documents as repairs, </P>

<P>alterations, change of occupancy, addition, historic building, or moved building. Alterations shall further be classified as Level 1 or Level 2. Any required elevation certificate shall be prepared by a certified land surveyor or registered professional civil engineer licensed in Virginia. </P>

<Sect>
<P>Exception: Construction documents or classification of the work does not need to be submitted when the building official determines the proposed work does not require such documents, classification or identification. </P>
</Sect>

<P id="LinkTarget_909">CHAPTER 2 </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>DEFINITIONS </H3>

<Sect>
<P>SECTION 201 GENERAL </P>

<P>201.1Scope. Unless otherwise expressly stated, the following words and terms shall, for the purposes of this code, have the meanings shown in this chapter. </P>

<P>201.2Interchangeability. Words used in the present tense include the future; words stated in the masculine gender include the feminine and neuter; the singular number includes the plural and the plural, the singular. </P>

<P>201.3Terms defined in other codes. Where terms are not defined in this code and are defined in the other International Codes, such terms shall have the meanings ascribed to them in those codes, except that terms that are not defined in this code and that are defined in the Virginia Construction Code </P>

<P>(VCC) shall take precedence over other definitions. </P>

<P>201.4 Terms not defined. Where terms are not defined through the methods authorized by this chapter, such terms shall have ordinarily accepted meanings such as the context implies. </P>

<P>SECTION 202 GENERAL DEFINITIONS </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>[A]</Lbl>

<LBody> ADDITION. An extension or increase in floor area, number of stories, or height of a building or structure. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>[A]</Lbl>

<LBody>ALTERATION. Any construction or renovation to an existing structure other than a repair or addition.</LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<P>&gt; </P>

<Sect>
<P>BUILDING. A combination of materials, whether portable or fixed, having a roof to form a structure for the use or occupancy by persons or property. The word “building” shall be construed as though followed by the words “or part or parts thereof” unless the context clearly requires a different meaning. “Building” shall not include roadway tunnels and bridges owned by the Virginia Department of Transportation, which shall be governed by construction and design standards approved by the Commonwealth Transportation Board. </P>

<P>CHANGE OF OCCUPANCY. Either of the following shall be considered a change of occupancy where the current VCC requires a greater degree of structural strength, fire protection, means of egress, ventilation or sanitation than is existing in the current building or structure: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>Any change in the occupancy classification of a building or structure. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Any change in the purpose of, or a change in the level of activity within, a building or structure. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Note: The use and occupancy classification of a building or structure, shall be determined in accordance with Chapter 3 of the VCC. </P>
</Sect>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>[A] </Lbl>

<LBody>CHANGE OF USE. A change in the use of a building or a portion of a building, within the same group classification, for which there is a change in application of the code requirements. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>[A] </Lbl>

<LBody>CODE OFFICIAL. The officer or other designated authority charged with the administration and enforcement of this code. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>[BS] DISPROPORTIONATE EARTHQUAKE DAMAGE.</P>

<P>A condition of earthquake-related damage where both of the following occur: </P>

<Sect>
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>The 0.3-second spectral acceleration at the building site as estimated by the United States Geological Survey for the earthquake in question is less than 40 percent of the mapped acceleration parameter SS. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>The vertical elements of the lateral force-resisting system have suffered damage such that the lateral load-carrying capacity of any story in any horizontal direction has been reduced by more than 10 percent from its predamage condition. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<P>[BE] EMERGENCY ESCAPE AND RESCUE OPENING. An operable exterior window, door or other similar device that provides for a means of escape and access for rescue in the event of an emergency. </P>

<P>EQUIPMENT OR FIXTURE. Any plumbing, heating, electrical, ventilating, air conditioning, refrigerating and fire protection equipment; and elevators, dumbwaiters, escalators, boilers, pressure vessels and other mechanical facilities; or installations that are related to building services. Equipment or fixture shall not include manufacturing, production or process equipment, but shall include connections from building service to process equipment. </P>

<P>EXISTING BUILDING. A building for which a legal certificate of occupancy has been issued under any edition of the USBC or approved by the building official when no legal certificate of occupancy exists, and that has been occupied for its intended use; or, a building built prior to the initial edition of the USBC. </P>

<P>EXISTING STRUCTURE. A structure (i) for which a legal building permit has been issued under any edition of the USBC, (ii) that has been previously approved, or (iii) that was built prior to the initial edition of the USBC. For application of provisions in flood hazard areas, an existing structure is any building or structure for which the start of construction commenced before the effective date of the community’s first flood plain management code, ordinance, or standard. </P>

<P>[BF] EXTERIOR WALL COVERING. A material or assembly of materials applied on the exterior side of exterior walls for the purpose of providing a weather-resisting barrier, insulation or for aesthetics, including but not limited to, </P>

<P>&gt; </P>

<Sect/>

<P id="LinkTarget_910">DEFINITIONS </P>

<P>veneers, siding, exterior insulation and finish systems, architectural trim and embellishments, such as cornices, soffits, facias, gutters and leaders. </P>

<P>[BF] EXTERIOR WALL ENVELOPE. A system or assembly of exterior wall components, including exterior wall finish materials, that provides protection of the building structural members, including framing and sheathing materials, and conditioned interior space from the detrimental effects of the exterior environment. </P>

<P>&gt; </P>

<P>[A] HISTORIC BUILDING. Any building or structure that is one or more of the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>Listed, or certified as eligible for listing, by the State Historic Preservation Officer or the Keeper of the National Register of Historic Places, in the National Register of Historic Places. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Designated as historic under an applicable state or local law. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>Certified as a contributing resource within a National Register, state designated or locally designated historic district. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>MOVED BUILDING OR STRUCTURE. An existing building or structure that is moved to a new location. </P>

<P>[BF] NONCOMBUSTIBLE MATERIAL. A material that, under the conditions anticipated, will not ignite or burn when subjected to fire or heat. Materials that pass ASTM E136 are considered noncombustible materials. </P>

<P>PRIMARY FUNCTION. A primary function is a major activity for which the facility is intended. Areas that contain a primary function include, but are not limited to, the customer services lobby of a bank, the dining area of a cafeteria, the meeting rooms in a conference center, as well as offices and other work areas in which the activities of the public accommodation or other private entity using the facility are carried out. Mechanical rooms, boiler rooms, supply storage rooms, employee lounges or locker rooms, janitorial closets, entrances, corridors and restrooms are not areas containing a primary function.</P>

<P>&gt; </P>

<P>REHABILITATION. Any work, as described by the categories of work defined herein, undertaken in an existing building. </P>

<P>&gt; </P>

<P>[A] REPAIR. The reconstruction, replacement or renewal of any part of an existing building for the purpose of its maintenance or to correct damage. </P>

<P>[BS] REROOFING. The process of recovering or replacing an existing roof covering. See “Roof recover” and “Roof replacement.” </P>

<P>[BS] RISK CATEGORY. A categorization of buildings and other structures for determination of flood, wind, snow, ice and earthquake loads based on the risk associated with unacceptable performance, as provided in Section 1604.5 of the International Building Code. </P>

<P>[BS] ROOF COATING. A fluid-applied adhered coating used for roof maintenance, roof repair or as a component of a roof covering system or roof assembly. </P>

<P>ROOF COVERING. The covering applied to the roof deck or spaced supports for weather resistance, energy performance, fire classification, or appearance. </P>

<P>[BS] ROOF RECOVER. The process of installing an additional roof covering over a prepared existing roof covering without removing the existing roof covering. </P>

<P>[BS] ROOF REPLACEMENT. The process of removing the existing roof covering, repairing any damaged substrate and installing a new roof covering. </P>

<P>[BS] SEISMIC FORCES. The loads, forces and requirements prescribed herein, related to the response of the building to earthquake motions, to be used in the analysis and design of the structure and its components. Seismic forces are considered either full or reduced, as provided in Chapter 3. </P>

<P>STRUCTURE. An assembly of materials forming a construction for occupancy or use including stadiums, gospel and circus tents, reviewing stands, platforms, stagings, observation towers, radio towers, water tanks, storage tanks (underground and aboveground), trestles, piers, wharves, swimming pools, amusement devices, storage bins, and other structures of this general nature but excluding water wells. The word “structure” shall be construed as though followed by the words “or part or parts thereof” unless the context clearly requires a different meaning. “Structure” shall not include roadway tunnels and bridges owned by the Virginia Department of Transportation, which shall be governed by construction and design standards approved by the Virginia Commonwealth Transportation Board. </P>

<P>[BS] SUBSTANTIAL DAMAGE. For the purpose of determining compliance with the flood provisions of this code, damage of any origin sustained by a structure whereby the cost of restoring the structure to its before-damaged condition would equal or exceed 50 percent of the market value of the structure before the damage occurred. </P>

<P>[BS] SUBSTANTIAL IMPROVEMENT. For the purpose of determining compliance with the flood provisions of this code, any repair, alteration, addition or improvement of a building or structure, the cost of which equals or exceeds 50 percent of the market value of the structure, before the improvement or repair is started. If the structure has sustained substantial damage, any repairs are considered substantial improvement regardless of the actual repair work performed. The term does not, however, include either of the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>Any project for improvement of a building required to correct existing health, sanitary or safety code violations identified by the code official and that is the minimum necessary to ensure safe living conditions. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Any alteration of a historic structure, provided that the alteration will not preclude the structure’s continued designation as a historic structure. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>[BS] SUBSTANTIAL STRUCTURAL ALTERATION. </P>

<P>An alteration in which the gravity load-carrying structural elements altered within a 5-year period support more than 30 percent of the total floor and roof area of the building or struc</P>

<Sect>
<P>&gt; </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_911">DEFINITIONS </P>

<P>ture. The areas to be counted toward the 30 percent shall include mezzanines, penthouses, and in-filled courts and shafts tributary to the altered structural elements. </P>

<P>[BS] SUBSTANTIAL STRUCTURAL DAMAGE. A condition where any of the following apply: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>The vertical elements of the lateral force-resisting system have suffered damage such that the lateral load-carrying capacity of any story in any horizontal direction has been reduced by more than 33 percent from its predamage condition. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>The capacity of any vertical component carrying gravity load, or any group of such components, that has a tributary area more than 30 percent of the total area of the structure’s floor(s) and roof(s) has been reduced more than 20 percent from its predamage condition, and the remaining capacity of such affected elements, with respect to all dead and live loads, is less than 75 percent of that required by the International Building Code for new buildings of similar structure, purpose and location. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>The capacity of any structural component carrying snow load, or any group of such components, that supports more than 30 percent of the roof area of similar construction has been reduced more than 20 percent from its predamage condition, and the remaining capacity with respect to dead, live and snow loads is less than 75 percent of that required by the International Building Code for new buildings of similar structure, purpose and location. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>TECHNICALLY INFEASIBLE. An alteration of a facility that has little likelihood of being accomplished because the existing structural conditions require the removal or alteration of a load-bearing member that is an essential part of the structural frame, or because other existing physical or site constraints prohibit modification or addition of elements, spaces or features which are in full and strict compliance with the minimum requirements for new construction and which are necessary to provide accessibility. </P>
</Sect>

<P>&gt; </P>

<Sect/>
</Sect>
</Part>
</TaggedPDF-doc>
